Robert Patterson Hughes Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Robert Patterson Hughes Papers 1876-1994 (bulk 1898-1909)
MSS82579
Hughes, Robert Patterson, 1839-1909
45 items
2 containers plus 1 oversize
.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States army officer. Correspondence, diaries, writings, printed memorial, biographical material, and photographs documenting Hughes's military career, including his account of the Battle of Little Bighorn written the following day as aide-de-camp to Gen. Alfred Howe Terry and material relating to his service during the Philippine insurrections (1898-1901).
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Hughes, Robert Patterson, 1839-1909.; Terry, Alfred Howe, 1827-1890.
Organizations
United States. Army--Officers.
Subjects
Little Bighorn, Battle of the, Mont., 1876.
Places
Philippines--History--Philippine American War, 1899-1902.; Philippines--History--Revolution, 1896-1898.
Occupations
Army officers.
Provenance
The papers of Robert Patterson Hughes, army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Patterson Hughes French and his wife, Elizabeth H. French, in 1993 and 1994.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Robert Patterson Hughes are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Robert Patterson Hughes (1839-1909) span the years 1876-1994, with the bulk of the material dating from 1898 to 1909. The collection consists of diaries, correspondence, photographs, writings, a printed memorial, and biographical material documenting aspects of Hughes's military career from his enlistment as a private in the 12th Pennsylvania Infantry in 1861 to his retirement as major general in 1903.
The bulk of the papers pertains to Hughes's service in the Philippines between 1898 and 1901. A series of six diaries kept between July 1898 and December 1899 chronicles Hughes's activities as inspector general of the Expeditionary Force from May 17 to August 1898, inspector general and provost marshal general of Manila from August 1898 to May 1899, and as commander of the Department of the Visayas after May 1899. A typed transcript is available for the first two volumes covering the period July to October 1898.
The papers also include a detailed account, accompanied by a hand-drawn map, of the Battle of Little Bighorn, written by Hughes to his wife on 30 June 1876. Hughes, then aide-de-camp to Alfred Howe Terry, arrived at the site of the battle on June 27th. His correspondence includes an 1893 letter from George D. Ruggles recalling the expedition's departure from St. Paul, Minnesota, to Fort Abraham Lincoln, North Dakota.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Battle of Little Bighorn, account of, 1876 (Box 1)
- Biographical material, 1909, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1893-1909, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
- Diaries (Box 1)
  - Original volumes (Box 1)
    - 1898, July 15-1899, Aug. 27, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1899, Nov. 10-19 (Box 2)
  - Typed transcript, 1994 (Box 2)
- French, Simeon Webster, account of 1863 encounter with Confederate forces near Romney, W.Va., 1885 (Box 2)
- Nozaleda, Bernardino, archbishop of Manila, Philippines, translation of two 1898 sermons, undated (Box 2)
- Photographs, undated 1898-undated 1899 (Box 2)
- Printed soldiers' memorial, 85th Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers, undated See Oversize (Box 2)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Printed soldiers' memorial, 85th Regiment, Pennsylvania Volunteers, n.d (Container 2) (Box OV 1)